Guide to the Glen Echo Chautauqua and Glen Echo Park Company records, 1889-1953 MS2133
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Glen Echo Chautauqua and Glen Echo Park Company records
1889-1953
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Cook, Richard
MS2133
9 Linear Feet
Collection contains financial records and press books. The material dates from 1889-1953. The collection includes records created by E & E Baltzley Realty Company, the National Chautauqua of Glen Echo, and Glen Echo Park Company.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Richard Cook in 2005.
Historical or Biographical Note
Glen Echo Park began in the late nineteenth century as a real estate enterprise and national Chautauqua, and subsequently grew into a major amusement park complex.
In 1888, Edward Baltzley purchased 516 acres in Montgomery County, Maryland. In 1889, he and his brother Edwin founded the E & E Baltzley Realty Company and began selling the property as residential lots. In 1891, they established the National Chautauqua of Glen Echo. Glen Echo was also home to Clara Barton and the headquarters of the American Red Cross in this period. In 1903, the Baltzleys lost their holdings in a foreclosure and the property was purchased by Washington Railway and Electric Company. In 1911, Washington Railway and Electric (under the name Glen Echo Park Company) decided to run their own amusement park on the site as a way to both boost weekend railway ticket sales and use surplus electricity. The park closed in 1968, and was obtained by the National Park Service in 1971.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains financial records and press books. The material dates from 1889-1953. The collection includes records created by E & E Baltzley Realty Company, the National Chautauqua of Glen Echo, and Glen Echo Park Company.
Collection Organization
Organized into 2 series: Financial records and Press Books.
Glen Echo (Md.); Amusement parks -- Maryland; Glen Echo Park (Md.) -- Chautauquas; Glen Echo Park (Md.); E & E Baltzley Realty Company; Baltzley, Edwin
- Financial records, 1889-1926; MS2133 Series 1; 6.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of financial records, including cash books, ledger books, check ledgers, journals, cancelled checks, voucher books, and sales books created by E & E Baltzley Realty Company, the National Chautauqua of Glen Echo, and Glen Echo Park Company. The materials range in date from 1889-1926. Of particular interest are the Sales Books, which contain Consolidated Daily Sales records. They record the date, weather, attendance, and detailed sales information for each day the park was open, and compare the daily record to that of the previous year. Also of interest are the Voucher Books, which provide weekly summaries of accounts payable, and the Comp Ticket Book, which records organizations (primarily church groups) that received complimentary admission to the park.
  - Cash book, 07/02/1889-08/31/1894 (Box 1)
    General note
  - Cash book, 11/21/1890-10/25/1898 (Box 2)
    Mold damage to first pages of ledger. Mold appears dormant, but is extensive.
  - Cash book, 05/30/1914-08/15/1917 (Box SHARED Box 23, Box 3)
  - Cash book, 05/20/1916-09/08/1918 (Box SHARED Box 23, Box 4)
  - Cash book, 05/15/1920-05/15/1926 (Box 5)
  - Journal book, 11/28/1890-10/25/1898 (Box 6)
  - Ledger book, 1890-1891 (Box SHARED Box 23, Box 7)
  - Ledger book, 1891-1893 (Box 8)
  - Ledger book, 1891-1898 (Box 9)
  - Sales book, 05/27/1911-09/07/1912 (Box 10)
  - Sales book, 05/24/1913-09/12/1914 (Box 11)
  - Sales book, 05/22/1915-09/09/1916 (Box 12)
  - Sales book, 05/19/1917-09/08/1918 (Box 13)
  - Sales book, 05/17/1919-09/20/1920 (Box 14)
  - Sales book, 05/14/1921-09/10/1922 (Box 15)
  - Sales book, 05/12/1923-09/14/1924 (Box 16)
  - Blank sales book, undated (Box 17)
  - Voucher book, 03/25/1911-06/08/1912 (Box SHARED Box 23, Box 18)
  - Voucher book, 06/01/1912-09/09/1912 (Box 19)
  - Voucher book, 05/31/1913-09/11/1915 (Box SHARED Box 23, Box 20)
  - Voucher book, 05/21/1921-09/14/1924 (Box 21)
  - Complimentary tickets book, 05/04/1924-09/08/1924 (Box SHARED Box 23, Box 22)
  - Check ledger No. 9--Lincoln National Bank, 05/15/1893-09/12/1893 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Check ledger No. 16--Columbia National Bank, 01/13/1892-04/16/1892 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Check ledger No. 17--Columbia National Bank, 07/05/1892-08/16/1892 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Check ledger No. 18--Columbia National Bank, 08/15/1892-09/15/1892 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Check ledger No. 20--Columbia National Bank, 10/11/1892-10/31/1892 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Check ledger No. 21--Columbia National Bank, 10/31/1892-11/19/1892 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Check ledger No. 22--Columbia National Bank, 11/19/1892-12/09/1892 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Check ledger No. 23--Columbia National Bank, 12/09/1892-01/03/1893 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Check ledger No. 24--Columbia National Bank, 01/03/1893-01/27/1893 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Check ledger No. 25--Columbia National Bank, 01/27/1893-02/23/1893 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Check ledger No. 27--Columbia National Bank, 05/13/1893-04/01/1893 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Check ledger No. 28--Columbia National Bank, 04/03/1893-04/21/1893 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Check ledger No. 29--Columbia National Bank, 04/21/1893-05/13/1893 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Check ledger No. 30--Columbia National Bank, 05/10/1893-06/01/1893 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Check ledger No. 31--Columbia National Bank, 06/01/1893-06/30/1893 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Check ledger No. 32--Columbia National Bank, 07/07/1893-08/03/1893 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Checks, 1892-1893 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Note, 01/03/1893 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Blotter paper, undated (Box 24, Folder 16)
- Press books, 1911-1953; MS2133 Series 2; 2.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of press books created between 1911 and 1953. The books contain newspaper clippings of both articles about Glen Echo Park and advertisements for the park. Also included in this series are several Filmsort Brand Aperture cards, containing images of the press books.
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 18)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 21)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 22)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 23)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 24)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 25)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 26)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 27)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 28)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 29)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 30)
  - Filmsort card, undated (Box 24, Folder 31)
  - Press book, 1911 (Box 25)
  - Press book, 1913 (Box 26)
  - Press book, 1914 (Box 27)
  - Press book, 1917-1923 (Box 28)
  - Press book, 1924-1925 (Box 29)
  - Press book, 1936 (Box 30)
  - Press book, 1944-1953 (Box 31)
  - Press book, 1948 (Box 32)
  - Press book, 1947 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Press book, 1952 (Box 33, Folder 2)